A Guide to the Clarence Paul Miles Papers, 1902-1955
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Clarence Paul Miles Papers, 1902-1960
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1961-003
0.2 cu. ft. 1 box
Papers of Virginia Tech graduate, professor of modern languages, and director of athletics Clarence Paul "Sally" Miles, including grade books for courses in French and German, together with personal memorabilia and photographs.
Miles, Clarence Paul, 1879-1966
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Clarence Paul Miles Papers were acquired by Newman Library prior to 1962.
Biographical Note
Clarence Paul "Sally" Miles was born in Hanover County, Virginia on June 21, 1879. The son of William J. and Charlotte Ellett Miles, he entered the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute (now Virginia Tech) in 1897. During his studies Miles played on both the baseball and football teams, serving as captain of each at different times. After earning his master's degree, Miles served as a chemistry instructor, while also coaching baseball and football. From 1902 to 1920, Miles served as the school's professor of modern languages and also served as the graduate manager of athletics, beginning in 1908. In 1920, Miles' part-time position as athletics manager evolved into the full-time director of athletics position, and he continued to serve in that capacity until 1935, when he resumed instruction in foreign languages. He retired in 1956, having also served as Virginia Tech's treasurer and as the dean of the college from 1943 to 1950. Among other activities, Miles served as a director and vice-president of Blacksburg National Bank and a member of the Blacksburg Town Council. He was twice married: first to Virginia Longley Vawter in 1913 and to Elizabeth Anderson Hall in 1935. Sally Miles died on May 2, 1966.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains papers of Clarence Paul "Sally" Miles, a Virginia Tech graduate (class of 1901), professor of modern languages (1902-1920, 1935-1951), and director of athletics (1920-1935). The majority of the collection consists of grade books for Miles' courses in French and German. Miles' grade records are kept in a set of identical books titled "The Teacher's Model Pocket Register and Grade Book." Each book contains the course title, names of students, and daily grade records, based on the system provided by the book publisher. Also within the papers are a small set of materials relating to Miles' life and Blacksburg, including a resolution of appreciation and a condition statement from the National Bank of Blacksburg, as well as two notes from local masonic lodges. The collection also includes three photographs: Miles in a VPI baseball uniform, Miles with Pete Willson, and an artists' conception of a planned addition to Miles Stadium.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by item type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following book was removed from the collection to be cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
A History of the Blacksburg Presbyterian Church ([Blacksburg, VA: The Church?, 1953?]).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Local Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives
Contents List
- Grade books, 1902-1904. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Grade books, 1905-1907. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Grade books, 1907-1911 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Grade books, 1911-1914. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Memorabilia and photographs, ca. 1903-1960. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - National Bank of Blacksburg resolution of appreciation, 1955.
  - Masonic birthday card, [1955].
  - National Bank of Blacksburg condition statement, [1955].
  - Notification of honorary membership in Blacksburg chapter of Royal Arch Masons, 1960.
  - Flyer for VMI-VPI football game, n.d.
  - Photographs
    - Miles in baseball uniform, ca. 1903.
    - Miles with Pete Willson, n.d.
    - Addition to Miles Stadium, n.d., [half-tone]